MDMA is like a deep breath
well thank God we're not trying to save
the world hey okay because we keep well
we are we are but we don't have to do
ourselves that's for sure
Jesus Christ well I don't think anyone
could
[Music]
well right now we are doing that
recording thing hello everyone this is
boys club auntie Madeline
stop manhandling me sir well
yeah it's cool it's good that's good you
know our time is short and so I'm gonna
try and jump to a question that it's
hard to pose actually to get the intent
right and to make it short okay
well you know we can work with the how
it comes out until it's really what
choice to be having said yeah what
bloody choice to be happy if we're
trying to do this okay so let's start
somewhere so so you might say that the
past is something we can learn from and
and the present is something to live and
the future is something to love if we
wanted to move forward healthily I mean
you could say a whole lot of other
things as well of course and there's
something that can happen when someone's
in the process of trying to learn from
the past that prevents them from doing
so we get set up we get sort of locked
you know yeah I think you are a man who
may be able to talk to that you know in
a rather interesting way I think that
there's been a way we're oh well I'll
certainly try better still now mate it's
it's all bollocks from here well
I think that the blocks that we have to
learning from our mistakes they're a lot
about you know self-criticism and
self-hatred and perfectionism and the or
there's something that will make people
realise an emotional aspect of it that
there needs to be a change or that there
needs to be a new truth there's
something about growth that needs to
happen that's postponed or resisted that
I was a master of resistance from my
early LSD trips and had very very
difficult led LSD trips and we just hold
on and wouldn't let go and wouldn't
learn and just wasn't capable of it then
I had a series of trips my first year of
college which eventually led me to you
know go to the guidance counselor and
learn about Stan Grof was to just take
it just try to have whatever I heard
about this mystical unit of experience I
want to know the truth I wanted to have
a different understanding I want to get
out of being confused and I would have
these very strong trips a lot of stuff
would happen I'd have these different
emotions but then I would I'd still be
like I you know I know I would have a
difficult time letting things happen I
would end up resisting and I would feel
just incredible friction of my brain and
then it was me doing it and I was fail
it was for me it was like even the
emotional circuits I wasn't prepared I
didn't have the capacity these are
strong emotions and I hadn't built up
even my capacity driving with a
lightning rod what they do and so I
think that there's a lot of different
ways that people get blocked and there
are some ways that we're learning about
how to unblock if people are willing to
do it and it's not just about the drug I
think that's very important to say that
it's drugs or other drugs but as 70a my
assistant psychotherapy for PTSD but
there's a voluntary part where the
people are ultimately healing themselves
and they have to choose to do so and
choose to face things and and so has to
be voluntary right some important thing
it has to come from the individual yeah
so we have a not I mean a very just to
give you an example we don't ever hand
MDMA to somebody right you know we put
it down and they have to take it
themselves when my very start and so
it's their own inner wisdom that we're
helping them with and they have to make
these decisions and come to feel certain
things and and so
once people recognize that - that it's
not so automatic taking pill and
something happens that you have to make
it happen and own it people can find
less punitive ways to relate to
self-criticism or they can be more self
loving and forgiving and just they have
a kind of relaxation I mean this rabbi
Zalman Schechter described MDMA as a
delight like the Sabbath right you know
a really yeah that's very very
interesting I mean there's something
about the relationship to light mmm that
so I mean with respect and motivation
it's something in front of you you know
it's something to move towards right but
it's all but it's also something that
that well yes I mean imagine if you're
in a cave and it's it's morning you need
to go out there into the day right I
mean it's also you know a mythological
motif you know that the Sun being
consciousness about the consciousness
and then things like this it is a primal
thing and I think sometimes in in a
certain mystical experiences you can
have there is also the movement towards
something you know sometimes but but but
but more generally it's important to set
goals you know and and there's an
interesting idea
yeah Eisenhower the General Eisenhower
you in president he has a saying that
planning is everything plans are nothing
you know I have you have to say your
goals but there's so many you know plans
that you make that keep getting sorted
by reality or just absolutely and
absolutely but the thing is you have to
make the plans in order to then judge
whether or not things are Co hearing
with them and the thing is where is that
where does the ability to set those
goals come from now I actually think I
actually think Rick that it comes from a
place that blurs the line between the
psychological and the metaphysical if
you take certain things into account I
well I feel that the impetus for me to
study psychedelics comes from multiple
generations be
me who were killed killed in the
Holocaust and in other ways so that if
that's what you mean that the goal comes
from life that happened before I was
even born well well I mean that makes a
lot of sense right I mean we are we are
creatures with the history we have
evolved over a very long time and you
might think that what also moves other
beings forward into life is is in some
sense the same essence that gives us
that capacity as well now in our lives
right now we can use many other words to
talk about things that are meaningful
and things to do but but there is
something I think really essential about
this this sort of a will to movement or
a will to life is philosophical ideas
but you know in order to in order to set
goals sometimes I feel you have to you
have to figure out where you are and
also where you've been and I guess with
MDMA we well how would you describe the
experience of MDMA hmm in in that way
that allows you to not only just accept
what you are now but tip what did to
deal with the past how do you even yeah
here's a okay there's a MDMA is like a
deep breath and it helps you to think
clearly to the ways in which our fears
block our thinking we don't want to
think certain things you know look at we
don't want to think that that ice can
actually be melting and we could be
changing the climate of the earth you
know and so we have people that reject
it with climate change denial and and
you know how can they how how is that
this is the earth cooling by the way
this is
Rick that news better have been
extremely important Rita is showing up
so then I guess I guess MDMA as a deep
breath
yeah and that by helping calm the
emotions you can think more clearly so
one of the veterans that was in our
study was long PTSD after friends were
killed and wounded in Iraq and he
described the healing from a medium dose
of 75 milligrams with this idea that he
he came to the realization that the PTSD
was his way of staying connected with
his friends who had been killed and this
was a sign of loyalty this was it wasn't
and but then he looked at it from there
every one of you and he said these
people are dead they wouldn't want me to
suffer they can't live they would want
me to live for them and he said now what
am I going to do with the rest of my
life and in that moment he healed
himself from PTSD and there was just
this well thank god we're not trying to
save the world hey okay because Jesus
Christ well I don't think anyone could
but at the same strange thing that every
individual is an individual and they're
responsible for themselves you know and
so in that sense there is that ultimate
responsibility right yeah that's very
scary actually and but it's about
finding your point of leverage like yeah
who are you knowing your past as you're
saying knowing what's the current
situation and where can you make a
contribution that's you know uses your
abilities and what the world needs in
some kind of pattern and yes you know
there is something about how
I thought a lot of people would actually
see psychedelics as a solution and you
know eventually it's turned out that
well they certainly can be they can be
remarkable solutions for and for lots of
people with with and about problems that
are so fundamental and and important to
all of us which is really quite
interesting and I think the title beyond
psychedelics I've come to understand
it's about you know what do we do with
them
absolutely they help us move beyond
those moments into our integration into
our daily life into our choices in the
world yes
absolutely I think that's a great
intention as a message and the thing is
of course the experience you have on
psychedelics is at least in big part a
product of the life you've been living
and what you've been doing and who you
are now we might talk about fundamental
themes we all go through right and
that's and that's yeah but the specifics
of how they manifest like the
particulars you know yeah it's obviously
continuous with the life you're living
and also where you're already aiming and
that's and that's the well it has to be
that way for them to be useful and
important otherwise it would be in just
some strange escape with no relevance to
the world but of course it is deeply
relevant to the world but also something
that my word it requires a certain it's
a certain kind of serious attitude it's
not it's not as though you there isn't
still the lightness and fun and these
different things but these are powerful
things and yeah and although there's
there's so many different ways to help I
mean people can you know pick something
example and yeah and that's doing good
that's moving things forward and yeah
over time you see what's right for you
or yeah yeah I have the my son and
daughter have both graduated college
just this last month oh that's awesome
and so they're both in this like you
know how do you choose what you do yeah
Jesus
[Laughter]
the existential question damn college is
over
look they at least at least the question
the question is good the question is an
important way that's the crucial one
yeah because but but you can find it out
the answers you might not get in some
blinding flash well we might I suppose
it I suppose it could happen and of
course inspiration strikes if you're
doing anything create if there are lots
of different little things you do and
you take action on them and you do them
so the inspiration striking is something
that can all relate to however the
problem is sometimes that life is so
complicated that you know you really
have to step out there into the world
and see what works and what doesn't
before you can be totally sure and so
for anything complicated it's it's an
effort that you obviously have to stick
out for a long time yeah and that's
something obviously that you've been
able to do so incredibly well which is
very it's very impressive for me okay
the good fortune to see something change
over so in 1990 is when we first started
working with the Veterans Administration
to try to interest them in MDMA for PTSD
mm-hmm and we kept being rejected and
rejected and rejected it was there was a
dissent it was it was particularly a and
then just last year we were you know our
study is finally going to be conducted
inside someone who's affiliated with the
VA in a way but who's head of a major
Department of Psychiatry and so he
finally said yes to him do you might
research but it was the same one that
said no in 1990 so it's you know 27
years Jesus see somebody initially
fearful and resist them yeah and I think
the thing to say is that it doesn't seem
that long you know that's not a really
very long time it is a long time but
it's like it's a frame of reference
right yeah I think that you know if you
couldn't even see change in your own
lifetime you're lucky you're just born
at the right time and it's very
fortunate in terms of trans yeah but
sure I think for people to choose it's
like yeah I think you have long term
plans I mean you can have goals that are
really
long term and and then you you know
develop little efforts along the way to
do pieces of that totally totally I ever
I have a friend of mine a wonderful man
named Neville Christie you know
sometimes say if you're going to Rome
sometimes you need to go through Naples
and when you're in Naples you meet you
realize you might need to go to Venice
now I have no Geographic knowledge of
Italy so this going all over the place
overhead figuratively alright and and
but you know the point is you can
reassess along the way and and that's
exactly as it as it should be it needs
to be because you don't have all the
knowledge at the beginning and and you
don't have all the knowledge at the end
but you hopefully have a little bit more
anyway but Rick I know we don't have too
long together thank you for sharing this
time with me if I could ask you if I
could ask you one question sure it would
be go ahead so let's think about it
where are you aiming now Europe all
right we all ready hey mate are you
gonna burrow downwards in the very next
few days if not even potentially today I
haven't even checked but probably
tomorrow or Wednesday we're going to
receive a letter from the European
Medicines Agency interesting and it's
going to include this the results of
discussions that have taken place over
about six months so far and it's going
to include their scientific advice for
what we need to do for phase three in
order to make MDMA into a medicine then
we need to develop a a protocol and a
budget and then we need to raise
probably eight million dollars of which
I think we have almost a million already
and then we need to train about forty
therapists and then next summer 2019 I
hope we start phase three in Europe but
that's a rapid timeline and and we will
be starting phase three for FDA in
August okay so that's the organisational
aim now I suppose another question might
be ok no no it's it's I I mean I'm
interested in its going on yeah but also
I think it's always interesting to ask I
mean you probably got asked it's all a
lot so it's not a particularly valuable
base it's helpful to to formulate where
you hate well I like to be updating my
thinking is always valuable oh it's it's
it is it's sides you have to figure out
what the hell's going on Jesus but ok so
your role within this is probably quite
clear to you in certain respects but in
others I guess because things are so the
world is so complicated and dynamic and
dynamic and the community psychedelic
and otherwise is so large but just
taking a psychedelic
community aids is small in some respects
but large in terms of the different
voices in there yeah yeah even though
there are definitely binding features
there are different voices people are
different intentions quite different
intentions for the world fundamentally
if you were to just let them go off and
paint it on some virtual reality
page which which of course some people
are trying to do what what is it that
that what are the key features of the
community or a way to discuss the
current state of play and the value
associated with the integration of
psychedelics into our life and society
what are the fundamental features of how
that discussion should happen that you
believe absolutely need to be there and
kept vital and alive or are still vital
and alive well I'd say respecting the
fears and the questions of the other
people that you're negotiating
discussing one you know this society the
culture the FDA the regulator's the EMA
that there's they're coming from a place
of wanting certain there's certain kind
of requirements some irrational some are
not that rational some our denial of
reality some are really open that
there's just a way in which the first
part is listening to what the what
they're saying and trying to understand
what their concerns are
which may be somewhat different than
what they express them maybe they're not
always expressing them so it's to try to
understand what their real goals are and
then try to respond to those questions
so for us it's been the progress we've
made with the FDA has been from
listening to the FDA and then trying to
help them help us so it's the thing I
learned at the Kennedy School of
Government at Harvard getting my
master's PhD was to think of myself you
know as the you know chief of staff to
the decision maker you know I mean you
can also think of yourself as the
decision maker but the idea is that
you're trying to present a case as clear
and simple as you can then as weighted
and balanced as that and that
[Music]
what I've seen over time is things go
from one dose you know the consensus
sort of science and was the one dose of
MDMA caused serious neurotoxicity which
caused important functional consequences
which meant that research should be
either eliminated or you know struggled
with over a long period of time to a
place where the risks are generally
considered to be minimal from benefit so
I've seen that transition but it's from
becoming the ally in helping people
figure that out I mean I got I bought
the first monkeys for George Riccardi to
do studies because I wanted to know the
answers when that wasn't enough I got
myself and friends to go get spinal taps
to they could look at our cerebral
spinal fluid and tabah lights and trying
to prove to us how brain damaged we were
yeah incredible I think there's there's
so much wisdom in there because it's
fundamentally about recognizing that
there's a shared image we all want to be
a part of right and so it's a bonding
with what is fundamental between all
individuals it's the humanity it's all
we have to go through it's understanding
that we all have we all have goals and
and and yeah it's it's a very valuable
message well thank you very much
[Music]